in our last session we took a brief in
fact all two brief Glimpse at the
prodigious work of Saint Augustine
and I might mention here that from
Augustine through the Middle Ages and up
and into the Renaissance
the history of philosophical thought in
the western world was dominated by
Christian thinkers obviously there were
non-Christian thinkers who had some
significant contributions to make in the
development of Western thought but the
dominant players in that period of time
were Christian
intellectuals and of course that's not
the case today but it has been in
previous time periods now when we get
to the beginning of the second
Millennium that is to the 11th century
we meet a man who following in the line
of Augustine made a significant
contribution both to the realm of
Theology and to philosophy and I'm
referring of course to Saint Anselm
who became the Archbishop of Canterbury
Anselm like Augustine was both a
theologian and a philosopher and he's
most famous for three important works
that he wrote the first one that I'll
mention is the little book cardeus
homo
it's really a question mark Kar Dias
homo why the God man
and from a somewhat speculative vantage
point
Anselm was trying to give a rational
argument for the need or the necessity
of
a person who participated both in deity
and Humanity to function and to serve
adequately as a mediator for our
Redemption
and he also was asking the question in
this book why
an atonement
was an atonement necessary for God to
redeem his people and this is
significant in the history of theology
because Anselm really developed in
Greater detail than anyone had before
him the so-called satisfaction view of
the atonement namely that in the
atonement Christ satisfied the demands
of God's justice
by serving as our substitute in our
place and so the whole idea of vicarious
sacrifice was Central to the thinking of
Anselm and he saw in this the necessity
of God's having such satisfaction in
order for God not to compromise or to
negotiate his own justice but again our
greater concern today is for the
philosophical contributions of Anselm
and his two other works that are
important are the monologium and the
pros logium and the monologium
he begins to develop some of his uh
arguments
for the existence of God now Anselm
followed in the footsteps of Augustine
and adopted a concept that Augustine
himself had used as part of his own
personal Creed and that is the statement
Credo UT
in telegon
in that phrase what is being confessed
are these words I believe
in order that I might understand
now neither Augustine nor Anselm
was ever satisfied with a blind faith
which they consider to be a form of
credulity that was not in any way
virtuous
but rather though both subscribe to the
idea that in the final analysis God is
incomprehensible namely that we cannot
contain in our finite minds or our
finite intellect a total comprehensive
understanding of God nevertheless the
God who is has revealed himself to us it
with sufficient Clarity and particularly
in the Sacred Scriptures
to such a degree that we can at least
have an apprehensive knowledge of him
and those who put their trust in God and
their faith in God and the things of God
should never be satisfied with a
childish immature understanding of God
now I mentioned that because we live
again in a time that is one of the most
anti-intellectual periods in Western uh
Christianity
that is we are anti-mind and it's become
a virtue among Christians to embrace
what is called a childlike faith now of
course there is a point for a childlike
Faith insofar as as a small child puts
implicit trust in one who knows more
than the child does namely the parent
while they're very young at least that
doesn't last too long of course that we
as the children of God should have an
implicit trust in our heavenly father
just as a young child has that kind of
implicit trust in their Earthly parents
but this concept of a childlike faith
has come to mean to many people today
what I would call what Anselm would call
what Augustine would call A childish
Faith well they say I don't have to
think about the content of my faith
that's a destructive thing that Scholars
get into I'm just going to keep it as
simple as I possibly can and not be
engaged in any serious study of theology
or the word of God or anything else I'm
just going to keep it simple now at that
point
when we take that position we sin
it's so far from being a virtue it is a
vice according to the New Testament
because the New Testament tells us and
commands us
that we are to be babes and Evil
childlike
in our sin
but in understanding
we are to be men that is we are to be
adults and as the author of Hebrews
labors that it is a sin to be satisfied
with the milk
and we are commanded as we seek maturity
in Christ to the diet of the meteor
things of the faith now this is the kind
of thing
that both Augustine and Anselm were
jealous to communicate
that the content that God has revealed
in his scripture
is content that was designed to be
understood by his people
and that we must seek
to gain as much understanding as we
possibly can
of that which God has provided for us
now again we know at the outset that we
can't possibly have a comprehensive
understanding of God
but we should not allow that
to lure us into an ungodly kind of
skepticism
or negligence of his truth it is the
duty of the Christian
not only to believe but the purpose of
belief is that in order that it's a
purpose Clause here we might understand
and now that takes work and it takes
hard work it means we have to study and
think clearly and so on to gain a deeper
understanding of God now with this
and some believed that the Christian
faith was rational
now because of that and because of his
heavy use of Reason in his philosophy
many have called him a rationalist
but when we talk about rationalism
where reason is placed above divine
revelation
that would be a slanderous appellation
to make to Anselm and some believe that
Revelation was the ultimate source of
Truth not naked bear rational
speculation but like Augustine before
him he believed that that which God
reveals
is not irrational
it is to be understood in an
intelligible manner
and that we are seeked we are
responsible to apply our minds to the
deepest possible level of cogent
thinking in trying to understand The God
Who reveals himself
now
when he begins to develop his Arguments
for the existence of God
before we get to his most famous one he
started with with a simple argument in
the uh in the monologue
and that is this that if anything exists
or just put it another way whatever
exists
either
exists through something
or by means of something
or
it exists through nothing
that's a very simple uh distinction
either something whatever exists in this
world exists because it has been made by
something other than itself
or
it has come from nothing
and the point that Anselm wants to
establish at the very beginning
is that for something to come from
nothing is a manifest logical absurdity
now keep in mind here that we've already
looked at Augustine's doctrine of
creation where he says that God creates
things acts nihilo out of nothing
but what that means is that there wasn't
some pre-existent matter that God then
shaped and reshaped into the present
world
something that eternally coexists with
him
and what Augustine did not mean when
when he said that creation is ex knee
hello that things come out of nothing
by themselves that is with nothing
causing them to be because God is not
nothing God is something and the whole
reason why uh Augustine and Ansel and
others are pointing to the necessity of
a Creator is because of their conviction
that it's manifestly impossible for
something to come out of nothing by
itself
now I can't think of any principle more
rational than that and I can't think of
any pit of irrationality that has been
more frequently jumped into by modern
thinkers than that they use sometimes
more sophisticated language but as I
pointed out in my book not a chance that
it Still Remains impossible for
something to create itself because to
create itself it would have to be before
it was which means it would have to be
and not be at the same time and in the
same relationship and so to argue that
something comes into being out of
nothing by its own power is to jump into
a sea of pure absurdity
all right but then we get over into the
pros logium
which is
the most controversial and perhaps
interesting work that came to us from
Saint Anselm because it's in the pros
logium that he developed the famous
ontological argument for the existence
of God
usually when Christian thinkers look at
the traditional Arguments for the uh the
existence of God they'll boil down to
three or four the three most popular and
most famous are called the cosmological
argument for God's existence where you
reason from the cosmos or the world back
to its first cause or to a creator
or the teleological argument which is
the argument from design where we look
around and we see that that things seem
to operate for certain purposes or for
certain reasons and you can't have
design without a designer you can't have
purpose without somebody intelligently
planning the desired end and those are
two very famous arguments that people
work over again and again but the
ontological argument as it was spelled
out by ansem
is one that's exceedingly vexing
it's the kind of argument that easily
gives you an Excedrin headache number
one and for the most part it's been
dismissed and then Revisited and then
dismissed again through Western uh
philosophical history and even in our
own day there's been a Revival of
interest in anselms ancient ontological
argument now it's called
the ontological argument because it's an
argument from being
and
ontology is the science of being and we
while we looked at the pre-socratics and
heraclitus and Parmenides and Plato and
Aristotle we know that the metaphysical
aspect of philosophy is one that focuses
attention on ontology on being
now the ontological argument is called
the ontological argument because it is
an argument from being to
uh
to the existence of God
now the way Anselm
States the argument is extremely
important
because sometimes you can try to
shorthand this argument and miss the
whole point that Anselm was trying to
communicate and the way he did it was
this he says that God
is that then which
no greater can be conceived
God is that than which no greater can be
conceived again the shorthand version is
often stated this way that God is the
greatest conceivable being
it's interesting that Anselm didn't
state it that way his his articulation
of it is much more awkward but there was
a reason for that God is that being than
which no greater can be conceived
now that's that's the the primary
premise that he adds to that
that
for God to be
that which then no greater can be
conceived
he must
exist in reality as well as in the mind
that is he must have real being and not
just hypothetical being
because if you're thinking simply of the
idea of God that exists in your mind
you are not thinking about the God of
Ansel
because God is saying or Anselm is
saying that the god he's defining is the
greatest being conceivable and if you're
conceiving of the greatest being
conceivable as not existing
then we can come up with a greater being
than the one you're talking about the
one who actually is
because
existence is greater than non-being or
nothingness in the language that he is
using here now his chief
antagonist was a monk by the name of
gonalo
who took up arguments
against this somewhat strange
ontological argument for the existence
of God we're going to low argued and
said wait a minute
he said just because we can conceive
of the greatest Island conceivable
an island of which
no greater Island can be conceived
does not mean
that such an island exists
unless we have the power to conjure up
reality just by conceiving it
well and some said you're right gone
alone just because we can conceive of
the greatest conceivable Island
doesn't mean that such a conceivable
Island exists in reality
but the greatest conceivable island is
not the highest conceivable being
there's a difference between arguing for
that being than which no greater can be
conceived as being necessarily conceived
as actually existing than arguing that a
perfect island or a perfect horse or a
perfect man can be therefore thought to
exist in reality now what's going on
behind the scenes here and what's being
assumed tacitly in this way of thinking
is what's left for modern and later
philosophers to argue about but one of
the common views
is that what Anselm is is really saying
here
is
that you cannot think of being
without thinking of being
as being
non-existent being
is unthinkable
non-existent
islands are conceivable
as a mental concept but you cannot even
have a mental concept of non-existing
being
because being by definition
bees being by definition is
it is a necessary logical connection to
the very of idea of being to conceive of
it as
being
for example in his response to gonello
he would say
that it's impossible to have if you're a
rational person
it is impossible to have
the idea of a possible necessary being
because if a necessary being
is simply possible
then it's not really necessary
so now we have to think in terms of this
idea that becomes a central point of
focus later on in philosophy
particularly in Thomas Aquinas of the
idea of necessary
being
necessary being in this case is that
being which is both logically necessary
to assume
and ontologically necessary now that
distinction
between ontological necessity and
logical necessity we'll look at in
Greater length when we look at Saint
Thomas Aquinas but for now we mentioned
it only in passing that what Anselm is
driving at I think
is Again The Logical necessity of
a really existing being
again you cannot think of being
as not being
that introduces The Logical principle
that is one of the most weighty if not
the weighty logical proof for anything
there is and that is the impossibility
of the contrary
the impossibility of the contrary is the
rule that says
something cannot be
it's opposite
intellectually logically or rationally
so that the being who's greater than
which no other can be conceived cannot
even be conceived of
has not been
well if you have your Excedrin headache
take two aspirins and call me in the
morning